<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Violin on SnailShell</title>
  <link>https://powersnail.com/tags/violin/</link><link rel="self" href="https://powersnail.com/tags/violin/index.xml"></link><updated>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated>
  <id>https://powersnail.com/tags/violin/</id>

  <author>
    <name>PowerSnail</name>
  </author>

  <icon>https://powersnail.com/favicon.ico</icon>

  <description>Recent content in Violin on SnailShell</description>
  <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
  <copyright>en-us</copyright>
  
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>PowerSnail</name>
    </author>
    <title type="html">Engage the Pinky During Bow Change</title>
    <link rel="alternate">https://powersnail.com/2022/engage-pinky-in-bow-change/</link>
    <published>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</published>
    <updated>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated>
    
    <id>https://powersnail.com/2022/engage-pinky-in-bow-change/</id>
    <summary type="html">Nathan Cole talking about shifting the balance to the pinky during one of his master classes.[^nathan] During one of his masterclasses, Nathan Cole was helping a student with landing the a soft note after a series of spiccato.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img
    src=&#34;https://powersnail.com/images/nathan-cole.webp&#34; alt=&#34;A picture of violinist Nathan Cole playing during his master class, in green T-shirt.&#34;
        srcset=&#34;https://powersnail.com/images/nathan-cole-400w.webp 400w,/images/nathan-cole-600w.webp 600w,/images/nathan-cole-800w.webp 800w,/images/nathan-cole-1000w.webp 1000w,/images/nathan-cole-1200w.webp 1200w,/images/nathan-cole.webp 1280w&#34;
     width=&#34;1280&#34;  height=&#34;591&#34; &gt;

    &lt;figcaption&gt;Nathan Cole talking about shifting the balance to the pinky during one of his master classes.[^nathan]&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;During one of his masterclasses, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.natesviolin.com/&#34;&gt;Nathan Cole&lt;/a&gt; was helping a student with landing the a soft note after a series of &lt;em&gt;spiccato&lt;/em&gt;. She couldn&amp;rsquo;t get that note &lt;em&gt;piano&lt;/em&gt; enough, because the bow coming down from the air carried its own momentum that was out of her control. Nathan offered two major insights: first, don&amp;rsquo;t think of it as &amp;ldquo;landing&amp;rdquo;, but instead, a rolling motion that morphs into coasting rather than sticking a landing; and second, engage the pinky to lighten weight of the bow, so the bow keeps its angle constant. What she had been doing up to that point, was raising her arm to lighten the note, which lifted the frog of the bow, causing the bow to rotate slightly, the tip to drop, and then the bow would slap the string harder than she wanted as it engaged the string at a more direct angle. When she engaged the pinky and started to think about the control of the tip, the problem went away instantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I&amp;rsquo;m not currently practicing &lt;em&gt;spiccato&lt;/em&gt;, Nathan&amp;rsquo;s lesson on pinky engagement illuminates on another problem: shaky down bow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two common schools of thought about bow change: the most popular paintbrush method, which encourages a soft, flexible wrist as if painting a wall with a brush (demonstrated &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UmDEl-Rasj0&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;); and the method that supposedly belongs to Nathan Milstein: &amp;ldquo;I move it in one direction, and then I move it back in the opposite direction&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I was taught the former, and to be honest, I&amp;rsquo;ve rarely seen anyone who actually make that Milstein method work, other than Milstein himself. The vast majority of violinists do flex their hand and wrist at the frog, some more conspicuous, some subtle, but hardly as quiet as Milstein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the paintbrush metaphor is not a perfect one. The emphasis on flexibility in the wrist gives me the impression that bow change is a wrist-centric action. The wrist makes a flexing move, and the rest of the hand just go with the flow. Whenever my bow bounced, I thought to myself that it must be my wrist movement not being fluid enough. And I had never managed to fully fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was watching Nathan demonstrating that falling &lt;em&gt;spiccato&lt;/em&gt; with a straight bow, something clicked in my mind. My problem was not with the wrist, but the fingers. Too much flex in the fingers means that they no longer exerts the same amount of the force to the bow stick, so the frog is a little lighter, while unrelenting gravity keeps a constant pull at the center of mass, rotating the bow like a slight nodding. When the bow nods, the tip is lower and the frog is higher, so for a brief moment, the bow is doing exactly the same thing as the student&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;spiccato&lt;/em&gt; landing. Sort of like a tiny flap of a wave hitting the rock, and bouncing off into the air. That extra upward force propagates through the stick, causing the infamous down bow bounce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By engaging the pinky&amp;mdash;more concretely, exerting the pinky to resist the frog from rising&amp;mdash;the bow can be kept straight. It&amp;rsquo;s a somewhat paradoxical sensation: from a physical point of view, we want the force to be constant. But because the natural tendency is to soften the finger together with the wrist, my subjective experience is that the pinky needs to be proactive in that split second, to keep the bow straight. Our perception of force and movement don&amp;rsquo;t always match reality, so to achieve a desired result, sometimes we have to change our perspective and &amp;ldquo;cheat&amp;rdquo; our brain. Choosing the right perspective and the right metaphor is the magic ingredient of a great teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.violinist.com/discussion/archive/23953/&#34;&gt;https://www.violinist.com/discussion/archive/23953/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <category>posts</category>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>PowerSnail</name>
    </author>
    <title type="html">Sneaky Shift in Bach&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Preludio&lt;/em&gt; in Partita III</title>
    <link rel="alternate">https://powersnail.com/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/</link>
    <published>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</published>
    <updated>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated>
    
    <id>https://powersnail.com/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/</id>
    <summary type="html">Preludio (Prelude in some version) is one of Bach&amp;rsquo;s best violin pieces. From measure 17 to 28, a bariolage among three strings brings us a sublime polyphonic experience, with only single notes played detaché.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Preludio&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Prelude&lt;/em&gt; in some version) is one of Bach&amp;rsquo;s best violin pieces. From measure 17 to 28, a bariolage among three strings brings us a sublime polyphonic experience, with only single notes played detaché. The focus is usually on the bowing, but the left hand is not without challenge either, especially at speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img
    src=&#34;https://powersnail.com/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/bariolage-full.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Sheet music of the bariolage section&#34;
        srcset=&#34;https://powersnail.com/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/bariolage-full-400w.webp 400w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/bariolage-full-600w.webp 600w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/bariolage-full-800w.webp 800w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/bariolage-full-1000w.webp 1000w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/bariolage-full-1200w.webp 1200w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/bariolage-full.webp 1912w&#34;
     width=&#34;1912&#34;  height=&#34;1156&#34; &gt;

    &lt;figcaption&gt;Snippet from Preludio&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;From measure 20 to 28, the left hand descends one position every two measures. The most straightforward way is to shift at the beginning of measure 21, 23, 25, 27, and 28, using the third finger on A string, the first finger always pressing the lower note on D string, as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img
    src=&#34;https://powersnail.com/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/straightforward-shift.webp&#34; alt=&#34;The straight-forward version&#34;
        srcset=&#34;https://powersnail.com/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/straightforward-shift-400w.webp 400w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/straightforward-shift-600w.webp 600w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/straightforward-shift-800w.webp 800w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/straightforward-shift-1000w.webp 1000w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/straightforward-shift-1200w.webp 1200w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/straightforward-shift.webp 2693w&#34;
     width=&#34;2693&#34;  height=&#34;258&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&gt;

    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are two ways to hide this shift. The first is to squeeze your 3rd finger inward without shifting when the bow is still on the D string, and then to complete the shift by moving the 1st finger while playing the other three notes. But given how cramped the notes are on higher positions, that squeeze might be a bit awkward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second way is to delay the shift and hide it using the open E. In measure 20, the 1st finger is on C♯, the 2nd finger on A. If we don&amp;rsquo;t shift, we&amp;rsquo;ll begin measure 21 with 2nd finger on A, too. Then, when the bow is on the open E, shift the entire hand down a position, and substitute the 3rd finger on A, the 1st finger naturally falling on B. If you can shift within the duration of that E, there will be no audible shift. And this way, there is no squeezing, or awkward hand frame. Like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img
    src=&#34;https://powersnail.com/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/sneaky-shift.webp&#34; alt=&#34;The sneaky version&#34;
        srcset=&#34;https://powersnail.com/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/sneaky-shift-400w.webp 400w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/sneaky-shift-600w.webp 600w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/sneaky-shift-800w.webp 800w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/sneaky-shift-1000w.webp 1000w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/sneaky-shift-1200w.webp 1200w,/2022/bach-preludio-sneaky-shift/sneaky-shift.webp 2693w&#34;
     width=&#34;2693&#34;  height=&#34;269&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&gt;

    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, in the measure 22, no shift is needed. In measure 23, begin with 2nd finger on G♯, shift during the open string E, and end with 3rd finger on G♯. So on, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many opportunities in this piece to use the sneaky shift. Measure 67 begins a bariolage that exactly mirrors this sections on the lower strings, so does the technique. The two-string bariolages, like the ones from measure 13~16, also have a few places for sneaky shift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you study the fingering of great violinists, you&amp;rsquo;ll see a lot of creativity in how they achieve the balance between techniques, musicality, and ergonomics. Szeryng&amp;rsquo;s fingering of solo Bach is famous for its clever problem-solving skills, using tiny slides to avoid awkward string crossing, using stretches to avoid slides, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, it all depends on what kind of phrasing and tone you have in mind. A sneaky shift is great for that clean crisp sound, and an over-slide might be just what you need in a lyrical moment. Fingering is personal, because style is personal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reference&#34;&gt;
  Reference
  &lt;a href=&#34;#reference&#34;&gt;&lt;small&gt;##&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bach, Johann Sebastian. &lt;em&gt;Drei Sonaten Und Drei Partiten Fur Violino Solo&lt;/em&gt;. Bärenreiter Verlag, 1720, &lt;a href=&#34;https://imslp.org/wiki/6_Violin_Sonatas_and_Partitas,_BWV_1001-1006_(Bach,_Johann_Sebastian)&#34;&gt;6 Violin Sonatas and Partitas, BWV 1001-1006 (Bach, Johann Sebastian) - IMSLP: Free Sheet Music PDF Download&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <category>posts</category>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>PowerSnail</name>
    </author>
    <title type="html">A Warm-up for Chords: Bowing Planes Exercise</title>
    <link rel="alternate">https://powersnail.com/2022/bowing-planes-exercise/</link>
    <published>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</published>
    <updated>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated>
    
    <id>https://powersnail.com/2022/bowing-planes-exercise/</id>
    <summary type="html">Chord and Bowing Planes ## How do we roll a clean chord on the violin? Or, perhaps a better question: how do we consistently roll a clean chord?</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&#34;chord-and-bowing-planes&#34;&gt;
  Chord and Bowing Planes
  &lt;a href=&#34;#chord-and-bowing-planes&#34;&gt;&lt;small&gt;##&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we roll a clean chord on the violin? Or, perhaps a better question: how do we consistently roll a clean chord?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this short post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to focus on one element: bowing planes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are roughly speaking 7 planes in violin bowing (if we disregard triple stops): G, GD, D, DA, A, AE, and E. When you play on a single note, there is a bit of wiggle room. When you play double-stops, the bow must stay at the plane steadily and accurately. A little deviation from the plane will cause the sound to suffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, look at this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G_CY6pesFhs&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; of Hilary Hahn playing Bach&amp;rsquo;s Sarabande in B Minor, especially starting at 0:45 where the camera shows the bow angle. Her movement is so precise. When she draws the bow, the bow stays in that plane without any deviation. And when she reaches for a different string, the bow snaps to a different plane, and then when it snaps back, it was exactly the same angle as before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the &amp;ldquo;snap&amp;rdquo; being so swift, the music flows without any bump. This is because while her vertical movement is abrupt, the horizontal movement isn&amp;rsquo;t. When the elbow level changes, the forearm still draws the bow at a constant rate, so nothing sounds disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes persistent practice to reach such a mastery command of the bow. But even if you&amp;rsquo;ve put in the time and effort, sometimes you can still get the feeling that your bow arm can&amp;rsquo;t find the planes. We naturally get rusty from time to time, and it shows when we play something chord heavy like Bach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a little warm-up exercise that I use to prepare myself for chord-extensive pieces. It gives some anchors to where each plane is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise-one&#34;&gt;
  Exercise One
  &lt;a href=&#34;#exercise-one&#34;&gt;&lt;small&gt;##&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img
    src=&#34;https://powersnail.com/images/bow-planes-exercise-legato.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Legato Exercise&#34; 
        style=&#34;width:100%; height: auto;&#34;
    &gt;

    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, play a simple legato exercise, connecting each plane to the next. Since we are warming up the bow arm, keep your torso stationary. Change the plane with your elbow level only. The aim of this exercise is to find where the planes are, and get used to moving between them swiftly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you cross from a single string to a double-stop, the double-stop must immediately ring. For instance, when crossing from G to GD, you must hear both G and D equally well. If D is airy, the elbow hasn&amp;rsquo;t dropped far enough. If G is airy, the elbow has overshot. The same principle applies for when crossing from GD to D. G must stop immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you are looking for is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bow speed remains steady throughout the whole exercise. No stopping. No speeding up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bow angle is held steady in the plane when you play each note.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bow angle changes swiftly when you change the plane. No muddiness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise-two-dotted-rhythm&#34;&gt;
  Exercise Two: Dotted Rhythm
  &lt;a href=&#34;#exercise-two-dotted-rhythm&#34;&gt;&lt;small&gt;##&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When breaking a chord, we must choose where and when to move from one plane to the next. An early break can make the chord sound more unified and with a stronger momentum. A late break put more emphasis on the first few notes, which is crucial for phrasing in some situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, you should be able to break the chord anywhere on the bow. In his masterclass, soloist Kerson Leung instructed a student do a simple exercise for Bach: break the chord as early as you can; shorten the first double-stop as much as possible, while still make them ring. The aim, of course, is not to play every chord curtly, but to acquire the capability of breaking a chord at an arbitrary place without damaging the tone quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img
    src=&#34;https://powersnail.com/images/bow-planes-exercise-dotted-rhythm.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Dotted Rhythm Exercise&#34; 
        style=&#34;width:100%; height: auto;&#34;
    loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&gt;

    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can reify this exercise with dotted rhythm. Again, play with the same requirement as the first exercise: clean, immediate string crossing. Snap into the plane and draw the bow as steady as possible. Don&amp;rsquo;t fidget with the elbow level; if you didn&amp;rsquo;t arrive at the plane accurately, take a step back and redo the measure. Remember, the goal is to anchor your elbow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increase the dotted ratio as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise-three-advanced-string-crossings&#34;&gt;
  Exercise Three: Advanced String Crossings
  &lt;a href=&#34;#exercise-three-advanced-string-crossings&#34;&gt;&lt;small&gt;##&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img
    src=&#34;https://powersnail.com/images/bow-planes-exercise-string-crossings.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Advanced String Crossings&#34; 
        style=&#34;width:100%; height: auto;&#34;
    loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&gt;

    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;So far, we have limited ourselves in moving between neighboring planes. But chords can span up to seven planes, depending on the phrasing. Therefore, the third exercise is jumping from G-string to every other plane, and then jumping from E string backwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make a clean sound this time, we have one additional restraint. The passing planes in-between your targets must not make a sound. Your forearm still can&amp;rsquo;t stop, while your elbow level needs to jump through a bigger gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my experience, this is the part where you can &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; drill in the anchor of each plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;applying-the-exercise&#34;&gt;
  Applying the Exercise
  &lt;a href=&#34;#applying-the-exercise&#34;&gt;&lt;small&gt;##&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a chord from your repertoire, and deconstruct the chord into separated planes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img
    src=&#34;https://powersnail.com/images/deconstructing-a-chord.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Deconstruction of a Chord&#34; 
        style=&#34;width:100%; height: auto;&#34;
    loading=&#34;lazy&#34;&gt;

    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, to deconstruct the first chord of Bach&amp;rsquo;s Sarabande of B Minor, we separate the chord into double-stops and single notes, according to what phrasing you&amp;rsquo;d like. Use dotted rhythm to experiment with different momentum and emphasis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;
  Conclusion
  &lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion&#34;&gt;&lt;small&gt;##&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this little 3-minute exercise is to anchor your elbow, to etch into your muscle memory the location of each bowing plane. You want to hear steady tone, consistent angles, and swift string crossings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download the whole exercise &lt;a href=&#34;https://powersnail.com/files/Bowing_Planes_Exercise.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is licensed under &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/?ref=chooser-v1&#34;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy practice!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <category>posts</category>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
