<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>dessert on SnailShell</title>
  <link>https://powersnail.com/tags/dessert/</link><link rel="self" href="https://powersnail.com/tags/dessert/index.xml"></link><updated>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated>
  <id>https://powersnail.com/tags/dessert/</id>

  <author>
    <name>PowerSnail</name>
  </author>

  <icon>https://powersnail.com/favicon.ico</icon>

  <description>Recent content in dessert on SnailShell</description>
  <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
  <copyright>en-us</copyright>
  
  <entry>
    <author>
      <name>PowerSnail</name>
    </author>
    <title type="html">Tiramisu</title>
    <link rel="alternate">https://powersnail.com/2022/tiramisu/</link>
    <published>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</published>
    <updated>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated>
    
    <id>https://powersnail.com/2022/tiramisu/</id>
    <summary type="html">Inspirations My recipe is loosely adapted from this recipe, with sparks of inspiration collected from here and there.
The Cream To me, the essence of tiramisu is mascarpone.</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&#34;inspirations&#34;&gt;Inspirations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My recipe is loosely adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.askchefdennis.com/the-best-tiramisu-you-will-ever-make&#34;&gt;this recipe&lt;/a&gt;, with sparks of inspiration collected from here and there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cream&#34;&gt;The Cream&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the essence of tiramisu is mascarpone. The creamy, milky fragrance, and the smooth texture are what make tiramisu so delicious and rich. Some recipes use additional heavy creams, but it&amp;rsquo;s unnecessary. Mascarpone is made from cream; all the flavors you like about cream are already inside mascarpone. Just buy enough mascarpone, and you have one less thing to whip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make the creamy curd of tiramisu, first whip 4 egg yolks in a double boiler. Prepare a small pot with a bit of water, bring it up to a boil, and turn the heat down to a simmer. Place a bowl above the steam, and whisk the egg yolk for about 10 minutes, until it&amp;rsquo;s thick, viscous, and of a lighter color. Gradually add 60g of sugar during the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve found that adding all the sugar at once can make the whipping process very awkward, especially with non-fine sugar. The mixture becomes simultaneously sandy and liquidy, which not very easy to work with. So, I add sugar in 3 batches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While waiting for the yolks to cool down, whisk the mascarpone just a little, so it&amp;rsquo;s fluffier. It&amp;rsquo;s very easy to over-whisk mascarpone, so be careful. Fold in the yolks when they are cooled to room temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optionally, drop a pinch of salt into the egg whites, whisk it to a stiff peak, and fold it into the cream as well. The whites have no flavor; all it does is to firm up the texture, and dilute the sweetness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;coffee&#34;&gt;Coffee&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepare 250g of coffee. Instant coffee works. As a coffee lover, this is not something that I thought I was ever going to say; but for tiramisu, it absolutely works. Double the powder to water ratio, so it&amp;rsquo;s strong enough. Or if you have an espresso machine, that&amp;rsquo;s even better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For extra fragrance, I steeped a bag of Earl Grey in the hot coffee for 2 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add a teaspoon of whatever liquor you like. Or if you are like me, who cannot drink actual alcohol, a few drops of rum extract works wonders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;assembly&#34;&gt;Assembly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roll the ladyfingers in the coffee, and place them nicely in a layer. They should be just wet enough, so that there&amp;rsquo;s enough liquid to work their way to the core over the next few hours, but not so much that the whole piece is dripping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top them, spread a thick layer of cream. And layer the ladyfingers and creams until everything is used up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary-card&#34;&gt;Summary Card&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a printable summary card for the recipe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img
    src=&#34;https://powersnail.com/images/tiramisu.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Summary Card&#34; 
        style=&#34;width:100%; height: auto;&#34;
     width=&#34;543&#34;  height=&#34;236&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <category>posts</category>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
